Guide to the Gwendolyn Bennett Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Gwendolyn Bennett Papers
1918-1976
JWJ MSS 106
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.63
(2 boxes)
Bennett, Gwendolyn, 1902-1981
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from William Reese Company on the Danford N. Barney, Jr. Fund and the George B. Alvord Fund, 2013.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Gwendolyn Bennett (1902-1981)
Gwendolyn Bennett, American writer and artist, was born to Joshua Robin Bennett and Mayme Abernathy on July 8, 1902. When her parents divorced in 1909, Bennett became estranged from her mother and was raised in Brooklyn, New York, by her father and stepmother, Marechal Neil Bennett.
Bennett attended Brooklyn's Girls' High (1918-1921) and then studied fine art at Columbia University (1921) and the Pratt Institute, where she graduated with a degree in fine arts in 1924. While still an undergraduate, Bennett published poetry in Crisis (November 1923) and Opportunity (December 1923), and also created cover art for the former (December 1923 and March 1924).
Upon graduation Bennett taught fine art at Howard University before moving to Paris where she lived from June 1925 to September 1926 and studied art at the Académies de la Grande Chaumière, Julian, and Colarossi, and at the École du Panthéon. Bennett also studied art at the Barnes Foundation in Merion, Pennsylvania, for which she received a scholarship (1928).
Bennett published poetry in Opportunity, Crisis, Palms, and Gypsy and contributed to anthologies, including Caroling Dusk (1927) edited by Countée Cullen and The Book of American Negro Poetry (1931) edited by James Weldon Johnson. Bennett also wrote a column for Opportunity, "The Ebony Flute" (1926-1928), and served as editor for Black Opals (1927).
Throughout her career Bennett balanced administrative and teaching positions with her artistic life. She taught at the Tennessee Agricultural and Industrial State College and the Federal Art Teaching Project, worked for the Department of Information and Education of the Welfare Council of New York, served as the director of the Harlem Community Art Center, and as a correspondent for the Consumers Union. Bennett married Alfred Jackson, a doctor, in 1928 and they remained married until Jackson's death in 1936. They lived in Eustis, Florida, and Hempstead, New York. In 1941 Bennett married Richard Crosscup, a teacher.
Bennett died of congestive heart failure on May 30, 1981.
Scope and Contents
The collection provides evidence of the personal and professional life of Gwendolyn Bennett. The papers are comprised of correspondence, writings, and personal papers, which shed light into Bennett's career as a writer and educator, as well as her private life, particularly her relationship with her parents.
Correspondents include Langston Hughes, who accompanied his letters with four poems inscribed to Bennett: "Hotel Boy" (1926), "Stalingrad" (1942), "Goodmorning, Stalingrad" (1943), and "Give Us Our Peace" (1945). Correspondence between Bennett and her father Joshua Bennett, mother Mayme Abernathy Pizarro, and stepmother Marechal Neil Bennett, in particular, provide insight into Bennett's life and work.
Evidence of Bennett's writing career, including mock-ups for her column for Opportunity, "The Ebony Flute," and drafts of articles and a short story, can be found in the papers.
The papers also contain personal papers, including bills, receipts, a book of Psalms, and notes that provide further insight into Bennett's personal life.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence, 1918-1971. II. Writings, 1926-1976. III. Personal Papers, 1925-1929.
African American authors -- 20th Century -- Archives; American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Harlem Renaissance; Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Women authors -- 20th Century -- Archives; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Poets -- United States -- 20th Century; Bennett, Gwendolyn, 1902-1981; Hughes, Langston, 1902-1967
- Correspondence, 1918-1971; Series I
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains Bennett's personal and professional correspondence reflecting her career and personal relationships. Most notably the series contains letters from Langston Hughes (some of which include poetry) and correspondence between Bennett and her parents. The letters between Bennett and her parents are particularly rich and contain insight into Bennett's experience as a writer and artist.
  - Abeworthy, F. M., 1926 August 28 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bennett, Joshua and Marechal, 1918-1929 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
    Includes letters from Gwendolyn Bennett.
  - Herring, James Vernon, 1937-1941 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Horne, Frank, 1968-1971 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Hughes, Langston, 1928-1946 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Jackson, A. J., 1929 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Pizarro, Mayme Abernathy, 1926-1935 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - ---, Flora, 1947 October 6 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Letter from Gwendolyn Bennett to Flora.
  - General Correspondence, 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Empty envelopes (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Writings, 1926-1976; Series II
  Arranged chronologically.
  This series is comprised of drafts of writings and mock-ups relating to Bennett's writing career, most notably her column for Opportunity, articles, and to a lesser degree, poetry.
  - "Ebony Flute," Opportunity, mock-ups, 1926-1928 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Poems, typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Includes poems from Caroling Dusk ("Hatred," "Sonnet") and The Book of American Negro Poetry ("Heritage," "Sonnet - 2").
  - Articles, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Includes "Towards a Permanent Bureau of Fine Arts," "Portraits in Color," "Tokens," "An Almost True Story," and "The James Weldon Johnson Literary Awards."
  - Untitled, "Chapter One," typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Untitled, typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    The first line is: "It seemed from the beginning that Bob was marked for a fearless life of tremendous adventure."
  - "The Buttonwood Hollow Bulletin", 1968 July 22 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Brown, Lloyd L., "Paul Robeson Rediscovered," Occasional Papers Series, Number 19, American Institute for Marxist Studies, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Personal Papers, 1925-1929; Series III
  This series contains bills, receipts, a book of Psalms, and other papers regarding personal matters.
  Not arranged in any particular order.
  - Bills and receipts, 1925-1929, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Psalms, with photographs and newspaper clipping enclosed, 1925, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Note regarding Eustis, newspaper clipping regarding Howard University, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)